（网飞公司）
制作公司
双重挑战公司
序  幕
（极北之地 1857年）
Captain!
船长！
Can we talk?
能聊聊吗？
We must break through the ice.
我们必须破冰前行
The men are hungry and exhausted.
大家都很饿 也累坏了
We cannot keep up this pace without consequence.
要是继续这样下去 恐怕会付出代价
Listen up, men!
大家听着！
The more we delay the labor, the firmer the grasp of the ice will become.
我们拖得越久 冰就冻得越牢固
The work continues.
继续干活
Rotate each group.
各组轮流作业
Sir, with respect…
先生 请听我说
The men need assurances.
大家需要一句准话
Assurances?
准话？
Yes, that we will head back to St. Petersburg once we free the ship.
对 就是让船动起来之后 我们会回圣彼得堡去
They don't think we'll be seaworthy for long and they want to know--
他们觉得我们的船航行不了多久了 他们想知道…
Listen up!
都听好了！
It is neither your place, nor the officer here, to think anything…
别的任何事情 都不是你们和这位长官该考虑的
We signed up for a mission and we will see it to completion.
我们接受了一项任务 就要把它完成
We will reach the North Pole.
我们一定会到达北极
Is it understood?
都听明白了吗？
An explosion, Captain.
船长 那里爆炸了…
About two miles away.
离这里大约三公里
Get the men.
去救人
The sled dogs are unharmed.
雪橇犬没受伤
Then where does all this blood come from?
那这血是哪来的？
Over here, Captain!
船长 在那里！
A wounded man, he's lost a lot of blood.
有个受了伤的人 他流了好多血
Wound to the shoulder, his leg is broken.
肩膀受伤了 腿断了
Bear attack?
是被熊咬的吗？
I don't think so, Captain.
我觉得不是 船长
Larsen, help me with his boot.
拉森 来帮我把这只靴子脱下来
A prosthetic leg.
是个假肢
Put him on the board.
把他抬船上去
Hurry! To the ship! Now!
快 抬上船 赶紧！
Larsen, that thing is coming.
拉森 那东西来了
Ready the rifles!
步枪准备！
On my command.
听我指令
Aim!
瞄准！
Fire!
开火！
Next group!
下一组！
Fire!
开火！
All to the ship!!
全部上船！
Where is that man we brought onboard?
我们抬上船的那个人呢？
Where?
他在哪里？
What is that thing? What does it want?
那究竟是什么东西？它想干什么？
Bring him to me!
把他给我！
The blunderbuss. Larsen, get the blunderbuss!
喇叭枪 拉森 拿喇叭枪！
Victor.
维克多
Victor!
维克多！
I killed it.
我杀了它
It's still alive!
它还活着！
Ladder!
梯子！
Pull up the ladder!
快收梯子！
Bring him to me!
把他交出来！
How many shots are left?
还剩几发？
One, but it can't kill it.
一发 但杀不了它
I know.
我知道
I'm not aiming for him.
我也不是要打他
Laudanum, to ease the pain. Drink it. Drink it.
这是鸦片酊 能止痛 喝吧
Where am I?
我这是在哪里？
You are on the Royal Danish ship, Horisont.
这是丹麦皇家航船霍莱松特号
I'm Captain Anderson. This is Dr. Udsen.
我是安德森船长 这位是邬德森医生
How many of your men did it kill?
那怪物杀了你们多少人？
Six.
六个
It will come back and kill many more.
它会回来 让更多人丧命
All of you, if necessary, unless you deliver me to it.
要是不把我交出去 你们都会没命
No, no. It's gone.
不会的 它不在了
It sank in the freezing waters. It's dead.
它沉入了冰水 死了
No, it is not!
它没死！
It cannot die.
它死不了
I have tried to destroy it.
我一直尝试彻底摧毁它
Whether you believe me or not,
不管你们信不信
it will come back… for me.
它都会回来 找我
And when it does,
等它真的回来了
you must promise that you will put me out on the ice
一定要把我送到外面的冰面上
and let it take me.
让它带走我
Please.
求你们了
What manner of creature is that?
那究竟是什么？
What manner of devil made him?
是什么样的魔鬼造出来的？
I did.
是我
就是我
I made him.
是我亲手造的他
I had determined that the memory of my evils should die with me.
我本已下定决心 让那些罪恶的记忆和我一同消亡
It's ready.
准备好了
Some of what I will tell you is fact.
接下来我要说的话 有些是真的
Some is not, but it is all true.
有些是假的 但这是真的
My name is Victor.
我叫维克多
Victor Frankenstein.
维克多·弗兰肯斯坦
It was my father who gave me that name.
我的名字是父亲起的
Do you know what it means?
你知道这名字是什么意思吗？
I believe I do, yes. Conqueror.
应该是征服者的意思
One that wins it all.
赢得一切的人
Yes. It all started with him.
没错 一切因他而起
My father.
我的父亲
And my mother.
还有我的母亲
Victor!
维克多！
第一部分
维克多的故事
Victor!
维克多！
Come down, your father is arriving.
快下来 你父亲来了
Maman?
妈妈？
I'm here, Mother.
母亲 我在这里
I'm here.
这里
My father was a baron and a preeminent surgeon.
我父亲是男爵 也是个杰出的外科医生
He had married my mother largely out of convenience,
他娶我母亲 很大程度上为了利益
as her dowry was considerable and her lineage noble.
因为母亲的陪嫁相当丰厚 而且她是贵族出身
It furnished my father with the means to preserve his rank and family estate.
她带来的资金 足以让父亲维持爵位和家族产业
He was absent from our lives,
日常生活中 从来看不见父亲的身影
but when he came home, the entire household bent to his will.
而每当他回到家 所有人都对他唯命是从
Claire, dear.
亲爱的克莱尔
The rest of the time…
他不在的时候…
Victor.
维克多
Father.
父亲
The rest of the time, Mother was mine.
他不在的时候 母亲就是我一个人的
No, bring that here.
别拿走 端到这里来
The salts in the meat will enrich your blood,
肉里的盐分能滋养你的血液
as well as the baby's.
还有胎儿的
You eat for two, remember?
一人吃 两人补 记得吗？
Go on.
吃吧
It's nutritious.
很有营养
Guardian angel.
守护天使
Sweet companion.
甜蜜的陪伴
Stand by my side and do not leave me.
请守护我 不要离开我
Under your mantle, shelter me, and…
用你的披风庇护我 然后…
I would hear them through the wall, arguing incessantly,
我隔着墙听到他们争论不休
yelling at each other about wealth, estate… and me.
对着彼此大吼大叫 话题关于财富和庄园 还有我
Their voices filled me with fear.
他们的争吵声让我万分恐惧
Maman?
妈妈？
The man despised us both.
那个男人鄙视我们两个
Our raven black hair, our deep, dark eyes.
讨厌我们乌黑的头发、深色的瞳孔
Even our quiet, at times nervous disposition
就连我们喜好安静、不时紧张的性情
seemed to exasperate him to no end.
似乎也会让他大为光火
List as accurately as you can the ancient classification
古代把体液分为哪几类？
of the humors in the human body.
尽量说精确一点
Blood, black bile, yellow bile, and phlegm.
血液、黑胆汁、黄胆汁和黏液
Average male heart. Weight?
男性心脏的平均重量是多少？
Nine to eleven ounces, Father.
250到310克 父亲
Average female heart. Weight?
女性心脏的平均重量？
Eight to ten ounces.
230到280克
Why do you suppose that is?
你为什么觉得
Difference in mass in female heart?
女性的心脏会轻一点？
Depth of emotion?
是因为她们情感更强烈？
Tendency to the melancholic?
更容易忧郁吗？
Mass. Volume of blood, Father. Muscular irrigation.
因为质量 血流量 肌肉灌注的不同 父亲
Quite. There is no spiritual content in tissue,
没错 人体组织中没有精神物质
and no emotion in a muscle.
肌肉中没有情感
Now, describe the main function of the tricuspid valve, please.
那么 请描述一下三尖瓣的主要功能
I cannot recall, Father, but I'm sure I will remember.
我现在想不起来了 父亲 但我肯定能想起来
Yeah, I'm sure you will.
嗯 我相信你
Ivory does not bleed, Victor.
象牙不会流血 维克多
Flesh does.
但人体会
By the time you remember a fact, your patient could be dead.
等你想起了某个知识要点 恐怕你的病人已经一命呜呼了
You understand?
懂了吗？
The main function of the tricuspid valve
三尖瓣的主要功能
is to prevent the reflux of blood into the vena cava.
是防止血液反流至腔静脉
No, not your hands. Not anymore.
不打手了 再也不打了
They are now the instruments of your craft and will,
它们如今是你施展技艺的工具 是你意志的延伸
and we must care for them.
要好好保护
Your face, however, is vanity.
而你的脸 就微不足道了
You bear my name, Victor, and with it my reputation.
维克多 你沿用了我的名字 也必然要维护我的名声
I pray you remember that.
我恳请你牢记这一点
I feel you have something very good, parce que…
我感觉你有很好的牌
Three…
三
Two…
二
One…
一
That's impossible.
不可能
I'll shuffle.
我来洗牌
Mother?
母亲？
Maman?
妈妈？
Father!
父亲
Father. It's Mother.
父亲 母亲出事了
Maman.
妈妈
I need hot water and clean linen. A lot of it.
准备好热水和干净的亚麻布 多拿一点 快
-Now. -Sir.
是 先生
-No, Victor! -Mother?
-不 维克多 -妈妈？
-Maman! -Victor!
-妈妈! -维克多!
Father! Father!
父亲！
-Victor! -Save her, please!
一定要救她 求你了！
My mother, whom I had come to consider a part of my very self,
我的母亲 我曾将她视作我的一部分
she who I thought would never leave,
我曾以为她永远不会离去
she who was life… was now death.
以为她是我的生命 如今她死了
Her eyes extinguished,
她的双眼已暗淡无光
her smile feeding the cold earth.
笑容被冰冷的土地埋葬
Leave!
走开！
All of you, leave!
都给我走开！
A part of the universe had been hollowed out
我的世界空了一块
and the firmament was now permanently dark.
我的头顶笼罩着永远的黑暗
Now, cover your eyes.
遮住眼睛
Don't look until I tell you to.
我叫你看再看哦
Now.
看吧
William grew full of sunshine and smiles.
威廉在阳光和笑容中长大
He was of a calmer, gentler disposition, clearly favored by my father.
他的性情比我平和温顺 显然更讨父亲喜欢
Thank you, Father.
谢谢你 父亲
Oh, it's a pleasure, my boy.
不客气 儿子
He was the breeze, I was the storm cloud.
他是宜人的微风 我是滚滚的黑云
He was all laughter, I was all frowns.
他带来欢声笑语 我让人愁眉不展
Pick up the reins.
拿起缰绳
Look at me, Father. Look at me.
父亲 看我做得怎么样
There was something more.
不止如此
Or rather, something was missing.
更确切地说 某些东西被忽视了
My mother had died
我的母亲
at the hands of the most distinguished doctor of his day:
死在如日中天的名医
My father.
我的父亲手下
An idea… took shape in my mind.
我的脑中渐渐有了个想法
Define the circulatory system, if you will…
请说说《心血运动论》中…
Inevitable, unavoidable…
无可避免 无法逃避
…as enunciated in De Motu Cordis.
…对循环系统是怎么定义的
…until it became truth.
…直到这个想法被说了出来
Father?
父亲？
You let her die, did you not?
你没救她 对吗？
I did everything in my power to save her. You must know that.
我用尽全力救她了 你必须知道这一点
So you failed.
这么说 你失败了
-No one can conquer death.
没人能战胜死亡
I will. I will conquer it.
我能 我会战胜的
Everything you know, I will know. And more.
我会掌握你掌握的所有知识 还会更进一步
I think we've done quite enough for today.
今天就到此为止吧
I was born anew that night.
那晚我重生了
I had a vision.
我看到了幻象
I saw, for the first time…
我第一次看到了
the Dark Angel.
黑暗天使
And it made me a promise.
它向我许下承诺
I would have command over the forces of life and death.
我将能掌控生死
I would become every ounce the surgeon my father was.
成为和父亲一样杰出的外科医生
I would surpass him in ambition and in reach.
我的野心和成就将超过他
Guardian angel.
守护天使…
The vision was so clear.
幻象如此清晰
Clearer than anything I'd ever seen in my waking hours or dreams.
无论清醒还是睡梦中 我都从未看到如此清晰的景象
But how?
但承诺如何兑现？
My downfall was swift.
我的境遇很快一落千丈
Two revolts and a fire on my mother's plantations
母亲的种植园 经历了两次叛乱和一场火灾
dwindled the family fortune.
家族财富因此锐减
We kept the estate, but lost everything else.
庄园留下了 但别的全都没了
William went to one side of the family in Vienna
威廉被送去了维也纳的亲戚家
and I to London, then Edinburgh.
我去了伦敦 然后又去了爱丁堡
And there, for decades, I tried to…
在那里 我花了数十年时间
expand the narrow limits of academia.
尝试为狭隘的学术界拓宽边界
Life.
生命
（皇家医学院纪律法庭 1855年）
This… is life, gentlemen.
这就是生命 先生们
We are born.
我们出生了
And no sooner do we rise, we fall.
刚上去没多久 就掉下来了
Death.
死了
And in the space between that rise and fall,
这一起一落之间
our humble little purview.
就是我们渺小卑微的一生
Now, birth is not in our hands.
出生不为我们所控
Is it?
对不对？
Conception, that spark, the animation of thought and soul.
生命之火的点燃 思想和灵魂的诞生
That is in God's hands.
掌握在上帝的手中
God.
上帝
But death.
而死亡
Ah, now there lies the challenge.
挑战正在此处
That should be our concern.
死亡应该掌握在我们手中
It should be.
应该如此
Who are we to do so? We are not gods, are we?
我们凭什么能掌控？ 我们又不是神明 对不对？
But if we are to behave as immodestly as gods,
但要是我们能像神明那般大胆
we must, at the very least, deliver miracles.
那至少能够创造奇迹
Wouldn't you say?
是不是？
Ignite a divine spark…in these young students' minds.
在年轻学子心中点燃神圣火花
Teach them defiance rather than obedience.
教导他们抛弃顺从 违抗权威
Show that man may pursue nature to her hiding places and stop death.
展示人类有可能掌控自然奥秘 让死亡不再发生
Not slow it down, but stop it entirely!
不是延缓死亡 而是长生不老！
Silence. Silence!
安静！
How exactly do you propose to teach what is impossible?
这种不可能的事 你究竟要怎么教？
Composite subject, the body.
人类的尸体 一个复合实体
That of a shopkeeper, delivered mere moments after expiration.
这是某个店老板 刚咽气没多久就送到了我这里
The brain laid bare but functional,
大脑暴露在外 但仍能运作
the spinal branches and vagal nerves intact.
脊神经分支和迷走神经完好无损
You may observe the hair-thin scars.
大家或许能看到一些极细的伤口
No coarse stitching needed by my own technique.
我的手艺无需粗糙的缝合
The arm, you see,
看这条手臂
comes from another specimen, that of a carpenter.
来自某个木匠
The muscles, ligaments, nerves, all connected now.
肌肉、韧带、神经 都已连结好
Now, the spasmodic movement of the body
看啊 电流导致躯体痉挛
caused from the electric current, this is not new.
这已不是新鲜事
It's not new. However, the flow of energy through the body
大家都见过 不过 这种躯体内的能量流动
follows a different notion entirely.
遵循一种完全不同的概念
An Eastern notion called qi.
一种称为气的东方概念
Now, it considers the vital flow of energy both within and without.
这种概念认为 生命能量的流动 同时存在于身体内外
I'm utilizing needles in six--
我用针在六个…
Quiet! Sit down!
安静！都坐下！
This is a hearing, Doctor, not a carnival act.
医生 这是听证会 不是狂欢节表演
You're not helping your cause, Victor.
你这样无济于事 维克多
This galvanic trickery will simply not do.
这种用电的诡计根本没用
Trickery.
诡计
Trickery?
诡计？
Are you sure?
你确定吗？
That is not trickery. That is a decision.
这不是诡计 而是一种抉择
Motor coordination between the eye of one dead man and the arm of another,
一个死人的眼睛 和另一个死人的胳膊协调运动
infused with a new will and the rudiments of understanding.
注入全新的意志和基本的理解力
Understanding in a brain that already died?
已经死亡的大脑也有理解力吗？
Release now.
放开
Please.
请放开
"Please" always helps.
礼貌一点总有效果
Turn that off at once. At once, you charlatan.
赶紧关了吧 你个江湖骗子
This is the future. This is possible.
这就是未来 这是有可能实现的
Why not study it? Why not quantify it?
为什么不研究一下 量化一下呢？
This is unholy. An abomination. An obscenity!
这是罪恶的 可恨、下流！
God gives life, and God takes it, Victor.
生命由上帝赐予 由上帝收回 维克多
Perhaps God is inept!
或许上帝就是无能！
And it is we that must amend his mistakes!
要由我们来纠正他的错误！
Do not let these old fools extinguish your voice!
别让这些老蠢货阻止你自由表达！
The answers only come when coaxed by disobedience,
只有采取不盲从的态度 摆脱恐惧和恃强凌弱的教条
free of fear and cowardly dogma!
答案才会浮现！
Professor Krempe.
克伦佩教授
Baron Frankenstein, my name is Heinrich Harlander,
弗兰肯斯坦男爵 我叫海因里希·哈兰德
and I carry with me a letter of introduction
我这里有一封
from your brother, William.
你的弟弟威廉写的介绍信
From my brother?
我弟弟？
I asked for the privilege of your acquaintance.
我希望能有幸认识你
It won't take but a minute of your time.
耽误你一点时间
-Please. -Very well.
-请进 -好
So William is coming to see me, is that it?
这么说 威廉要来看我 对吗？
Yeah, in a matter of days.
对 几天后到
He wants to introduce you to his fiancée. My niece, as it happens.
他想让你见见他的未婚妻 也就是我的侄女
Elizabeth Harlander, a very nice young lady,
她叫伊丽莎白·哈兰德 是一位非常可爱的小姐
fresh from convent life.
刚刚从修道院学校毕业
The photographs are mine.
这些照片都是我拍的
William has become quite successful in the world of finance.
威廉在金融领域很有成就
He's making a name for himself.
弗兰肯斯坦的名声越来越响了
Ha! A name? For himself?
哎哟！是吗？
Well, I'm afraid we both share that name, whether we like it or not.
要知道我们都是弗兰肯斯坦 不管我们乐不乐意
I read your article in The Lancet.
我拜读了你在《柳叶刀》上的文章
You really believe you can do it?
你真的觉得这事能做到吗？
Assemble a man?
组装出一个人来？
A full new body? And give it life?
做出完整的全新人体？还要有生命？
You saw it today, didn't you?
你今天也看到了
What I saw was a crucifixion, really.
说真的 我看到的是你当众受难
You were done for before you uttered a word.
你还没开口说句话 就被钉死了
I still showed them.
但我还是向他们展示了
What?
展示什么？
The truth.
事实
They will forget by suppertime.
他们到晚餐时间就忘了
Yes, yes, yes. But what did you think?
话虽如此 你觉得怎么样？
I thought it was brilliant.
我觉得非常厉害
It was. I know.
没错 我就知道
But you are like a child, so excited,
但你有点孩子气 太激动了
clutching your new pet so tightly that you're strangling it.
紧抓你的新宠物 快把它勒死了
That is why I worry about you.
我不免为你担心
Can you contain your fire, Prometheus?
你能控制好火种吗 普罗米修斯？
Or are you going to burn your hands before delivering it?
还是没等把它交出去 就先烧伤了自己的手？
Quite.
说得对
Please do not think me rude, but my day has proven long enough,
请不要觉得我无礼 但这一天已经足够漫长
and I believe myself totally unfit for the company of strangers.
我的状态也完全不适合 再陪伴陌生人了
So if there's nothing more--
如果没有什么别的事了…
Oh, but there is. Much more.
还有重要的事
I've taken quarters in Edinburgh.
我在爱丁堡找好了住处
Three days from now, we are to meet with William and Elizabeth.
三天后 我们一起见威廉和伊丽莎白
And that evening, I will change your destiny.
我将在那晚改变你的命运
I will show you something extraordinary.
我会让你看到非同凡响的东西
The peach. The peach. Turn the peach. Turn it.
桃子 把桃子转过来
You bit it again.
你又啃了
You're eating the peaches.
你一直在吃桃
This is a memento mori.
这是对死亡的沉思
The peach, symbol of life and youth, and you bite into it?
桃子是生命和青春的符号 怎么就被你啃了？
-I was hungry, Kiki. -Don't call me Kiki.
-我饿了呀 小希 -别那样叫我
Baron Victor Frankenstein, sir.
先生 维克多·弗兰肯斯坦男爵来了
You can leave.
你可以下去了
Forgive me.
抱歉
Welcome.
欢迎
Herr Harlander.
哈兰德先生
A young art, photography.
这是一种新兴艺术 摄影
Goodbye, Kiki.
再见 小希
Already a passion of mine.
我已经迷上了
Did you bring the papers?
文件都带来了吗？
Oh, thank you.
谢谢
-You're extraordinary. -Thank you.
-你非常出色 -谢谢
You're using the nervous system to deliver the surge of energy.
你利用神经系统来传递能量脉冲
Are you not?
对吗？
Correct.
没错
And thus the sustainability of the life force you command
因此 你所操控的生命力 只能维持很短时间
is very brief, wanes, evaporates.
很快就会衰退、消散
How so?
为什么这么说？
At the lecture, you ended your demonstration out of pride.
当时你颇为自豪地结束了演示
But really, because the galvanic life force
但其实是因为 那股电流般的生命力
was already fading, was it not?
已经衰竭了 对吗？
Are you yourself a surgeon, sir?
先生 你是外科医生吗？
Yeah, once upon a time. An army surgeon.
曾经是 我是战地医生
Not a particularly skilled one, either.
医术也说不上多精湛
But it allowed me to secure the rudiments of my fortune.
但也给我打下了发家致富的基础
I own a few ammunition factories.
我现在有几家军火工厂
-An arms merchant. -A realist.
-你是军火商 -不如说是个务实的
Are you familiar with the Evelyn Tables?
你对伊夫林解剖图表熟悉吗？
Of course. Acquired by Sir John Evelyn,
当然 那是约翰·伊夫林爵士当年
there are four planks, meticulous dissection,
买下的四张人体标本精细解剖图
some of the oldest in Europe, presenting the nerves,
是欧洲最早的人体神经 和动静脉解剖图
veins and arteries of cadavers. What?
为什么会提到这个？
Yes. But there's a fifth one.
因为还有第五张
The most compelling one.
这张最让人信服
Exquisite, is it not?
非常细致 是不是？
Flesh rendered onto wood.
呈现于木头上的鲜活血肉
The cadaver lies on the plank, is peeled away layer by layer,
尸体放在木板上 逐层剥离
and the remaining tissue is lacquered with resin onto the wood.
用树脂将剩下的组织固定在木板上
-It showcases the lymphatic system. -Yes.
-这是淋巴系统 -没错
Muslim medics called it the secret circulatory system.
穆斯林医学家称其为隐秘的循环系统
It moves a mere three liters of fluid, but it's a vast network.
仅仅输送三升体液 却构成了庞大的网络
-Oh, it's remarkable. -Yes.
-真是非同凡响 -确实
Now for us, for you, the important variation is here.
现在对我们 也是对你而言 关键的改变就在这里
The ninth configuration. A very delicate,
这第九种构造 环绕心脏的结构
almost ethereal structure surrounding the heart.
极为精巧 近乎空灵
It can distribute, but also store energy.
既能分配能量 也能储存能量
Yes, if you can access that without destroying
如果你能在不破坏周围组织的前提下
-the surrounding tissue-- -No. Not through the front.
-触达这一构造… -不 不是前面
The back, spinal column, thoracic curvature.
是后面 脊柱 胸曲
Of course.
没错
Flow of energy, scarring and regeneration beyond anyone's imagination.
远超人们想象的能量流动 瘢痕形成和组织再生
Life eternal.
永生
I will endow your pursuit with unlimited resources.
我将提供无限的资源 来支持你的研究
And in exchange?
那我要拿什么来交换？
No need to become indelicate.
这么说就俗了
We're searchers for truth and transcendence, kindred spirits.
我们探寻真理 志在超越 有着共同的追求
I may in time ask you for a favor in return,
某天我也许会请你帮个忙 作为回报
but it's mostly the privilege to record your process for posterity.
但最重要的是记录研究过程 以传诸后世的这份特权
I work alone.
我习惯独自工作
I'm very quiet.
我绝对不出声
William Frankenstein and your niece, Herr Harlander.
哈兰德先生 威廉·弗兰肯斯坦和您的侄女到了
I shall consider it.
我要考虑一下
I'll consider it.
我会考虑的
Baron.
男爵
Don't pretend to be reasonable now. It would be such a shame.
别假装冷静了 错过了就可惜了
Victor.
维克多
William!
威廉！
-Victor. -Look at you.
-维克多 -瞧瞧你
My, you've grown.
老天 你长大了
Through no merit of my own.
可惜不是我的功劳
May I introduce the woman I'm to marry.
来见见我的未婚妻吧
Lady Elizabeth Harlander.
伊丽莎白·哈兰德小姐
Absolutely delighted.
荣幸之至
Can't say I was shocked when you were expelled,
听到你被驱逐 说实话我也不惊讶
but the manner and virulence of your expulsion,
但他们的态度太强硬 言语太狠毒
uncalled for, I'm sure.
我认为实在没有必要
No, it was called for.
有必要
I earned it.
我应得的
I made it a point to earn it, wouldn't you say, Herr Harlander?
我特意挣来的 你说是不是 哈兰德先生？
It was quite an exit, I assure you.
确实声势浩大
Why provoke them?
为什么要激怒他们？
Why not just carry on without calling attention to yourself in such a manner?
何不继续做自己的事 避免惹来不必要的关注？
How safe, even by your standards, William.
威廉 就算以你的标准来看 这么做也太保守了
You almost sound like Father.
你这话听着都有点像父亲了
He was a most tactful man, our father.
父亲可是相当老练的
He was precise, discreet, measured.
他做事精准、谨慎、有分寸感
I, on the other hand, fail to see why modesty is considered a virtue at all.
我就不是 我完全不懂为何谦虚是一种美德
Victor's always been one to harvest attention.
维克多一直这么引人注目
Even as children, I mitigated his voice by staying silent.
即便在小时候 我也常常 通过保持沉默 来消解他的声音
Perhaps too much and far too many times, wouldn't you say, Victor?
这样的事发生无数次了吧 维克多 你说呢？
If life can be regenerated,
如果可以再造生命
not as a mere simulation,
并非简单的模拟
but as a divine act by physical, chemical means, why whisper it?
而是通过物理化学手段 如神迹般地再造 何不大声说出来？
You laugh?
你笑了？
-You're amused? -I must be, yes.
-你觉得好笑吗？ -没错
Are my ideas not clear?
我的理念没表达清楚吗？
You certainly expressed them loudly enough.
你显然已经够大声的了
Are they not worthwhile?
不值得为之努力吗？
Ideas are not worthwhile by themselves, I don't believe.
我认为理念本身并不值得为之努力
Enlighten me, please.
愿闻其详
Take the war, for example.
拿战争来说
William, cigar and brandy in my study?
威廉 去书房享用雪茄和白兰地吧
Surely you've heard my niece expound on the matter before.
我侄女的长篇大论你肯定都听过了
You'll excuse us.
我们失陪了
Pray, carry on. Ideas.
请继续说 关于理念
Well… honor, country, valor.
这么说吧 荣耀、国家、勇气
These surely are worthwhile, elevated ideas by themselves,
这些必然是值得为之奋斗的崇高理念
wouldn't you agree?
同意吧？
-Mm-hmm. -And nevertheless, men are dying for them.
然而 人们为了这些理念赴死
In a decidedly un-elevated way,
以一种显然毫不崇高的方式
face down in the mud, choking on blood,
脸埋在泥泞里 喉咙呛着血
screaming in pain.
痛得大喊大叫
Men that were fathers, brothers or sons to someone out there.
他们是某人的父亲、兄弟或儿子
Men that were fed, cleaned and nursed
他们被自己的母亲带到这个世界
and schooled into this world by their mothers,
被悉心喂养、洗净、照料、教育
only to fall on a battlefield far away,
最后却被送到某个遥远的战场
far from those that provoke these tragedies.
真正制造惨剧的人却躲得远远的
Those men remain at home, untouched by blood or bayonet,
他们好好地待在家中 不沾血 不挨刀
their skin unpierced, their blankets warm and clean.
皮肤完好无损 被窝温暖洁净
That is what happens when ideas are pursued by fools.
这就是蠢人追求理念的后果
And you think me a fool?
那你觉得我是蠢人
Run to your brandy and cigars.
快享用你的白兰地和雪茄去吧
The boys are waiting.
他们都在等着呢
How often a man believes he's met an angel or a devil,
一个人常常以为遇见了天使或魔鬼
only to find it is all an illusion.
到头来却发现一切不过是幻觉
The game of chess we play…
我们下的这盘棋
we play only against ourselves.
对手只有自己
Help him.
帮帮他
Help him!
快点！
Here you go. Drink some.
给 喝点吧
You better come with me.
快跟我来
Nothing.
什么都没有
Sir, the watchman saw him.
先生 看守人看到他了
Circling the ship. In the mist.
在迷雾中绕着船转
We all saw him drown.
我们都亲眼看他沉下去了
Sir.
先生
The men are terrified.
大家都很恐慌
They think that man should be surrendered to the ice
觉得该把那个男人扔到冰面上
and be done with this.
结束这一切
He is under my protection…
他受我保护…
and the protection of the Crown!
受王国庇佑！
A few weeks later, I rode with William and Harlander
几周后 我、威廉和哈兰德 骑马穿过海峡
to a lake near Vaduz across the channel.
来到瓦杜兹附近的一个湖边
The tower was built as a water filtration plant to irrigate the fields.
这座塔楼是用来过滤农田灌溉用水的
Public works, so construction was abandoned at the start of the war.
是个公共工程项目 所以战争一开始就被弃建了
Not this war, the one before.
不是这场战争 是前一场
Or the one before that, I cannot quite remember.
或者是再前面一场 我记不清了
The moment I laid eyes on it…
一看到它
The tower.
这座塔楼
I could feel destiny calling.
我便感受到了命运的召唤
The structure's basically intact.
建筑结构基本完整
And there's a chute going from top, right to the bottom.
这里还有一条陡坡道 从顶上直通到底部
I can arrange for your belongings.
我会安排人把你的个人物品
We'll bring them from Edinburgh.
从爱丁堡运过来
Anything you need or want shall be granted.
你需要什么 都能满足
-Anything? -Anything.
-什么都可以？ -什么都可以
I have secured William's service for the duration of the project.
整个项目期间 威廉随叫随到
I'll need a holding cell.
我要一个临时密室
-And an ice chamber close to the lab. -William.
-实验室旁边要有个冷库 -威廉
There are two pump reservoirs at the base of the tower.
塔楼底部有两个泵水库
We'll repurpose those.
要改造一下
We shall need to recondition the steam engines.
我们要重启蒸汽机
We'll need enough fuel to make sure they run.
需要足够的燃料 来保证机器正常运转
There and there, four high-capacity voltaic batteries,
那里 还有那里 放四块高容量的伏打电池
positive and negative polarity,
正负电极
and a lightning rod system of pure silver telescoping down into the lab.
还要一套纯银避雷针系统 向下延伸至实验室
Yes. My contractors can manufacture any and all equipment you may require.
没问题 你需要什么设备 我的承包商都能造出来
I take it then that we have an understanding?
那么 我们应该达成共识了吧？
A bargain has been struck.
交易达成
Bastard!
混蛋！
No. No. Not this one.
这个不行
Aah. Open your mouth.
张嘴
You, you're lucky to be hanged. You would have died within the year.
被绞死算你走运 你本就活不过今年了
Herr Harlander promised me access to optimal specimens.
哈兰德先生答应我 让我拿到最好的样本
Yeah, that he may have, your lordship,
阁下 他倒是答应了
but as you well know,
可您也知道
crime doesn't pay, and it's a poor showing of it we have here.
犯罪又不是什么好差事 我们这里也只有些歪瓜裂枣
They're wretches every one of them.
哪个都是可怜虫
I'm sorry about that.
真是抱歉
That's a strong back. This one will do.
背很强壮 这个可以
Come back later.
稍后再来
Confession?
来告解？
I was intrigued.
我很好奇
What would such a delicate, pious creature have to confess to?
如此纤弱又虔诚的人 能有什么要告解的？
As luck would have it, an opportunity presented itself,
真是碰巧 被我找到了一个机会
and I…
我…
I was about to find out.
我就要揭开谜底了
Bless me, Father, for I have sinned.
神父 请为我祝福 我有罪
How long has it been since your last confession, my daughter?
孩子 你多久没告解了？
Barely a week, Father. I was in a convent.
还没到一周 神父 我在修道院待过
A week?
就一周？
Tsk-tsk. Have you so hastily committed sin?
你就这么轻率地犯错了？
I have.
是的
Sin of intent, not deed.
是罪孽的念头 并非实际行动
-A man, is it? -Yes.
-因为一名男子 对不对？ -对
My fiancé's brother.
是我未婚夫的兄长
Lust?
是欲念吗？
Hatred.
是憎恶
Hatred…
憎恶…
-Hatred? -The man is appalling, grotesque.
-憎恶？ -那名男子很恶劣、很丑陋
Harsh words.
这样的话很是刺耳
Rather uncharitable, wouldn't you say?
近乎无情了 对吗？
Respectfully, Father, you do not know this man.
尊敬的神父 您并不了解这个人
He tries to control and manipulate everything and everyone around him.
他试图操控周围一切的人和事
Like every tyrant, he delights in playing the victim.
他和所有暴君一样 以假扮受害者为乐
His only advantage, I would say,
要我说 那是他唯一的本事
is he's far cruder than he believes himself to be.
他自以为绅士 实则粗鄙不堪
Cruder?
粗鄙不堪？
Uh, pray explain yourself, my child.
我的孩子 请详细说明
For one, he's easy to spot.
比如说 他太容易被发现了
You can see him… even on a busy street on market day.
即便是集市日的拥挤街道上 也能轻松看到他
Tell me, how soon did you spot me?
说吧 你什么时候发现我的？
I saw you well before you saw me, I can say that much.
只能说远比你看到我来得早
Have you had supper?
你吃过晚饭了吗？
I'm not that hungry, Baron. Thank you.
我还不怎么饿 男爵 谢谢
Well, I for one am famished.
我就饿坏了
-Thank you, my good man. -Thank you, sir.
-谢谢 好心人 -谢谢 先生
What books did you buy, hmm? May I?
你买了什么书？能让我看看吗？
Guess.
你猜
-Guess? -I'd rather that you did.
-让我猜？ -还是猜一下吧
Very well.
那好
A romance…
言情小说
drenched in Mediterranean sun and silk and the skirmishes of love.
沐浴着地中海的阳光 身着丝绸华服 沉醉于爱的纠葛
Insulting, but unsurprising.
真是无礼 但也不奇怪
Really?
是吗？
-Insects? -Mm.
昆虫？
My interest in science leans towards the smallest things.
我对科学的兴趣 体现在对微小生物的好奇上
Moving with nature, perhaps the rhythms of God.
它们随自然而动 或许是顺应上帝的节律
I've always searched for something more pure, marvelous.
我一直在寻觅 某种更纯粹、更奇妙的事物
Is that what you were seeking in the convent?
这就是你在修道院追寻的东西吗？
In a way.
算是吧
Was it worth it?
值得吗？
Is anything?
有什么是值得的吗？
Permit me, sister.
可以吗？
This hardly seems appropriate.
这样好像不大合适
Is anything?
有什么是合适的吗？
Very well.
很好
Laughter!
笑起来！
And for the very first time,
生平第一次
I became more interested in life
不知何故 我对生的兴趣渐浓
and somewhat less interested
对死的兴趣
in death.
减淡了
The main rod has a fast bolting system.
主杆采用快速螺栓固定系统
Did you use an alloy?
用合金了吗？
Copper and zinc.
铜锌合金
This is… This simply will not do. Start over.
这个不行 重来吧
Pure silver is a perfect conductor.
纯银是完美的导体
William, you must stay behind. Please.
威廉 你得留下 拜托了
I trust you above anyone else.
我最信任的就是你了
Only for a few more days.
再多待几天就行
You're not going to catch her.
你抓不到它的
Beautiful. Beautiful.
真漂亮
-Should we trap her or let her go? -Mm…
把它关起来 还是放走呢？
Trap her.
关起来
Now we have something in common.
这下我们有共同点了
A prisoner.
一个囚徒
As promised, William took dutiful charge of the laboratory build and needs.
威廉如约行事 认真负责建造实验室 满足各种需求
Can you fix that over there, please?
那边能修一下吗？
Go, help.
去帮一下
He followed my instructions to the letter.
他严格按我的指示办事
The battery.
电池
It's all pure silver now.
现在是纯银的了
Conduction points corresponding to the lymphatic system,
这是和淋巴系统相对应的传导点
which was quite complex. -But I managed.
非常复杂 但我做出来了
Mm-hmm.
嗯哼
Herr Harlander, thank you. The party's delightful.
哈兰德先生 谢谢 派对很精彩
I hope we're not distracting you from your research
但愿我们没有干扰你做研究
to tend to me and Elizabeth.
毕竟你还要顾着我和伊丽莎白
Not at all.
完全没有
She's young. She can count on us to guard her.
她还年轻 我们得护着她
I shall leave you your privacy.
我还是回避一下
No need for subterfuge between us.
我们之间还掩饰什么
French porcelain, chimes to a man's stream.
法国陶瓷 多么美妙的共响
I am very near a solution, an access point to the lymphatic system.
我快找到解决方法了 给淋巴系统确定传导点
Ah, yeah, that.
哦 那个呀
It's been so long.
这么久了
The war is waning.
仗快打完了
And my funding will end with it.
资金供应也快断了
You said your funds were unlimited.
你不是说资金无限供应吗？
My patience is not.
但我的耐心是有限的
I have it on good authority that a battle is to take place within a week.
我得到了可靠消息 一周内会爆发一场战斗
The tide of war will deliver its bounty to our shore.
战争好比潮水 会把战利品送到我们这条海岸上来
A battlefield? The bodies will be mangled.
战场上的尸体肯定一塌糊涂
One week.
就一周
-One week? -After that, history will pass us by.
-一周？ -一周后 创造历史的机会就会溜走
Flush that for me, will you, Baron?
帮我冲一下吧 男爵
A week to determine how to deliver the current.
一周内找到传递电流的办法
Impossible.
绝无可能
What would I do?
我该怎么办？
I was close. I could feel it.
就快成功了 我感觉得到
And then…life got in the way.
谁知横生阻碍
Oh.
哦
I believe she missed you.
它肯定想你了
I must warn you, Elizabeth, I've been working on a dissection.
伊丽莎白 我得先警告你一下 我在处理解剖体
It's beautiful.
很美
Does it shock you?
吓到你了吗？
Reminds me of martyrdom paintings.
让我想起了殉道主题的绘画
Pain is gone.
没有了痛苦
You can see God's design in the symmetry and the shapes.
在对称的构造和形状中 看得到上帝的精妙手笔
Elizabeth.
伊丽莎白
I must confess something to you.
我得向你坦白
I have a belief in the marvelous and so do you.
我相信这世间存在奇妙非凡之物 你也一样
There is a bond between us. Can you feel it?
我们之间有种默契 你能感觉到吗？
An almost physical one. I truly believe it to be something else.
一种近乎生理上的吸引 我坚信这种感觉绝非寻常
Believing something does not make it true.
你所信之物 未必是事实
Then why are you here?
那你为什么来这里？
Beautiful creature, is she not?
它很美 对不对？
Remote. Entirely bewitching, but so odd.
孤傲 令人沉迷 却又如此怪异
Three hearts.
有三颗心
Multiple eyes. White blood.
复眼 白色的血
And a fascinating lack of choice.
它无法做出选择 所以如此迷人
I don't understand.
我不明白
Choice is the seat of the soul.
有选择的能力 灵魂才能栖息
The one gift God granted us.
这是上帝对我们的赠礼
Elizabeth…
伊丽莎白
I have chosen.
我做出选择了
Good night.
晚安
Elizabeth!
伊丽莎白！
I thought I had failed.
我以为我失败了
I thought it was entirely over. I thought…
以为一切都完了 以为…
And I thought…
我以为…
And I…
我…
The symmetry.
对称性
God's symmetry. Yes, yes.
上帝创造的对称性 对
Yes.
找到了
Placing the battery above the lymphatic system.
把电池放在淋巴系统上
I had found the key.
我就这么找到了解题的关键
Nothing could stop me now.
再也没有什么能阻挡我了
Nothing.
没有
No! No, do not take any bodies
别动！这堆尸体
from the top or the bottom of the pile unless I mark them.
顶上的和底部的都别搬 就搬我做了标记的
Ice or rot may have destroyed the tissue.
冰冻或腐败可能会破坏组织
Look only in the middle.
就看中间的那些
Abundance can be disorienting unless one hones one's aim.
东西太多 会让人晕头转向 除非目标非常明确
I'm favoring tall specimens, long limbs.
我想要个子高的 长手长脚的
Scale will make the work easier.
划定范围 活就好干了
I like that.
我喜欢
Perfection.
尽善尽美嘛
And why not, dear Baron?
有什么不好呢 亲爱的男爵？
Indeed, why not?
确实 有什么不好呢？
Look for a head that's intact.
找到完整的人头
Put that one in the cart.
搬到车上去
Set that one over there.
那个放那边
Bring the others.
其他的送过来
Oh, good God.
老天
Do you mind?
劳驾
It is finished.
大功告成
Herr Harlander!
哈兰德先生！
A storm is coming!
暴风雨要来了！
My cane.
我的拐杖
My cane!
我的拐杖！
My cane, in the handle.
我的拐杖 手柄打开
Mercury.
水银
-Are you ill? -Thank you.
-你病了吗？ -谢谢
Is it… syphilis?
是梅毒吗？
Yeah, I'm dying.
对 我快死了
One night with Venus, a lifetime with Mercury.
一夜偷欢 终生服毒
Isn't that the phrase?
是这么说的吧？
What stage?
几期了？
Secondary?
二期？
We both know the precise schedule.
你我都清楚会怎么发展
It starts to eat away my bones,
已经在啃噬我的骨头了
orbital, cheek, teeth, jaw, skull, exposing my brain.
眼眶、脸颊、牙齿、下颌、颅骨 层层侵蚀 直到抵达大脑
Tumors, madness, excruciating pain.
长瘤、发狂、剧痛
One fine morning, I will start to scream and I will never stop.
到某个清晨 我会开始尖叫 停不下来
I cannot face such a vulgar demise.
我无法接受如此不堪地死去
Which brings me to my one condition.
于是我想到了我唯一的要求
Our deal. As agreed, in exchange
我们约定好的交易
for my generous intervention on your behalf.
我为你慷慨解囊所能换取的东西
And as we give life to our new Adam,
既然我们即将造出新人类
I want to be placed in this new perfect body.
我想要拥有这具完美新身体
No.
不行
-No, no. -Yes.
-不可以 -当然可以
Not now. Not now!
还没到时候！
-Precisely now. -We'll talk about this after, not now.
-正是这时候 -这事我们以后再聊 现在不行
There is no after!
哪还有什么以后！
There is no after.
没有以后了
I gave you everything you wanted!
你要的一切 我都给你了！
I give you everything you ask for.
你要什么 我都给你
Name it, it's yours.
随你说
Even Elizabeth.
你要伊丽莎白都行
Please.
求你了
"Please" always helps.
礼貌一点总有效果
The disease has spread all inside of you.
你已经病入膏肓了
It's systemic, and you know it.
这是全身性疾病 你知道的
Every organ in you is polluted.
你的每个器官都感染了
Your brain, your blood, it's all polluted.
大脑 血液 全都感染了
But my money's not, is that it?
但我还有钱啊 对不对？
It's impossible.
无济于事
Now, all you need to say is one simple word.
我只要你说一个“行”字
"Yes," no more and no less.
别的什么都不要说
No! Do you understand? No!
不行！听明白了吗？不行！
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
Stop!
住手！
Stop.
住手
If we lose that, we have nothing. We both lose.
没了这个 我们就一无所有了 我们俩都会完蛋
I will be the eagle that feasts on your liver!
普罗米修斯 我就是啄食你肝脏的鹰！
Please, stop!
求你了 住手！
Herr Harlander. Herr Harlander!
哈兰德先生！
Hold on, look at me!
坚持住 看着我！
No! Herr Harlander!
不！哈兰德先生
No, no. No!
不要啊
No, no, no!
不！
No!
No! No! No!
不！
You lied to me.
你骗了我
You lied.
骗了我
Victor!
维克多！
No, please.
别过来 求你了
Look. Same.
看 一样的
Sun.
太阳
Sun. Light.
阳光
Face it.
去感受一下
Sunlight. The sun is…
阳光 太阳…
The sun is life.
太阳是生命之源
Ah, the warmth. Huh?
很温暖
Yes! Yes.
没错
Victor.
维克多
-Victor. -Yes.
-维克多 -对
Yes, yes, yes. Of course you are.
对 你就是
Of course you are.
你当然就是
Victor.
维克多
The mail, sir.
邮件来了
Letters from the old estate.
老庄园来的信
Geneva.
日内瓦
-Is there anything from my uncle? -No.
-有我叔叔的来信吗？ -没有
Perhaps we should pay them a visit.
或许我们该去拜访一下他们了
Careful. Look. Look down.
小心 看着脚下
Water. Water.
水
Water.
Yes, water.
对 水
-Victor. -No, I'm Victor.
-维克多 -不 我是维克多
That's water. Come here.
这是水 来这里
-Victor. -Come now, come. All right, good.
-维克多 -来吧 很好
We're going to take a big step.
要跨一大步
We'll do it together. Ready?
我们一起来 准备好了？
This way, like this.
-走这边 这样 -维克多
No, not like that. This way.
不是那样 走这边
Oh, no, no, no. Hot, hot.
别碰 烫
No, don't touch. Don't touch that.
不能碰 别碰它
It's hot.
烫
Sit. Very good. Very good. Yes.
坐下 很好 真棒
Yes. Now, look what I have here.
好 看这是什么
Look at this. What is this thing?
看这个 这是什么？
What is this strange thing? Careful.
这个怪东西是什么？当心
You're very strong.
你力气很大
Yes. And like this. Huh?
好了 这样
Yes, you want another? Yes, this one goes right here.
还想要那个？好 这个放这里
Key.
钥匙
Victor.
维克多
This will keep you nice and warm.
这样你就不会着凉了
Nice blanket to keep you warm.
披上一条好毯子 暖暖的
-Victor.
维克多
All right.
好了
You stay.
你待在这里
You stay here now.
就待在这里
Stay here now.
待着别动
I'll be back. All right. Stay there.
我去去就回 待着别动
Victor.
维克多
No, no, no, no, no. It's all right.
别动 没事的
I'll come back.
我会回来的
Victor.
维克多
Everything was new to him.
对他来说 一切都是新的
Warmth, cold, light, darkness.
温暖、冰冷、阳光、黑暗
And I was there to mold him.
我的任务是塑造他
I never considered what would come after creation.
造成之后的事 我还从未考虑过
And having reached the edge of the earth,
来到世界尽头
there was no horizon left.
才发现没有地平线
The achievement felt unnatural.
如此成就有种非自然的感觉
Void of meaning.
并无意义
And this troubled me so.
这让我十分烦恼
Your men, they wish to go back.
船员们都想回去
Yes?
对吗？
Probably.
可能吧
But the moment we're free, we're setting sails forwards.
不过一旦船能开动 我们就会继续前行
No matter the cost.
不管付出什么代价
You share my madness.
你简直和我一样疯狂
Perhaps there is a finer point in me telling you my story.
我向你讲述自己的故事 或许别有深意
Whether there is or isn't, Baron…
男爵 不管是否如此
I'd like to hear it.
我都愿意听
Weeks passed,
几周过去了
and as his strength increased rapidly, mine waned.
他的力量迅速增强 我却日渐衰弱
Alas, no further language or development occurred.
可惜他没学会更多的话 也没有别的进展
No, no, no, no, no, no.
不对
Down, down, down, down.
低头
Yes, there we are.
这就对了
There we are. Stay there. Stay.
可以了 别动
Yes, that's you.
这就是你
That's you. All right?
这是你 知道了吗？
Oh, yes, this is healing rather nicely.
愈合得很好
I'm tired.
我累了
I have not slept.
我好久没睡了
Not a winky-dinky-doo of sleep for me.
一点都没睡
Tending to you.
一直在照顾你
I've finished shaving you.
终于给你脸上刮干净了
No, no, stop, stop.
不行 别动
Let go. No, no, no, no, no, no. Open.
放下 不可以 松开
Open your hand. Open. Open it.
手松开 快松开
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
Look. Look what you've done.
看看你都干了什么
You have to listen to me. You have to listen. I said drop it.
你要听我的话 我说了放下
Stupidity! No. Stop.
真蠢！不 别这样
Come here.
来
-Victor. -No, don't touch me!
-维克多 -不 别碰我！
Don't ever touch me!
永远都别碰我！
Come here.
来吧
I didn't do this. You did this.
不是我 是你自己弄的
The wound.
伤口
It's closed.
闭合了
But how?
怎么会的
All right.
好了
No, no, no.
不行
No.
别动
All right. All right.
好了
I'm sure everything's all right.
肯定一切都好
We'll be there soon enough.
很快就到了
I know you have thoughts. I know.
我知道你有想法 我知道
I know you do.
我知道你有
Somewhere in there. Somewhere in there you have thoughts.
就在这里面 你有想法
Hmm? Don't you?
是不是？
Something you might want to say?
你想说什么吗？
However jumbled, however confused?
虽然脑子里很乱、很困惑
Hmm? Something?
有想法吗？
Am I presuming too much?
还是我太心急了？
Victor.
维克多
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes!
知道了！
This much we have established.
这个已经教会你了
That is my name. My name is Victor.
那是我的名字 我的名字是维克多
Is there anything else that you can say? Anything at all? Hmm?
你还能说点别的吗？什么都可以
Anything? Anything?
有吗？
Um, sun, hmm?
太阳
Cold. Rain. Blood. Anything.
冷、雨、血 任何东西
Boot. Can you say "boot"?
靴子 靴子会说吗？
Victor.
维克多
No, yes, no, yes! How about…
够了！那么…
How about "hand"? Can you say "hand"?
手呢？手会说吗？
Hand. Hand.
手 说啊…
Oh. Oh, oh. You are afraid of me?
你这是怕我吗？
You're afraid of me?
你怕我？
Why? Why would you be afraid of me?
为什么？为什么你会怕我？
I'm not going to hurt you.
我不会伤害你的
I'm not going to hurt you. I made you.
我不会伤害你的 是我造了你
I'm your maker! Stop it!
是我造了你！别这样了！
You're here. You're really here.
你们来了 真的来了
Come on, then. Come, come.
来吧 快进来
I have to tell you. I have so much to show you, Elizabeth.
伊丽莎白 我得说 我有好多东西要给你看
You won't believe it. It's absolutely marvelous.
特别奇妙 你都不敢相信
Come, come, I'll show you my notes first.
快来 先给你看我的笔记
Is my uncle here?
我叔叔在这里吗？
What?
什么？
My uncle, is he here?
我叔叔 他在这里吗？
No, no.
不在
No, I'm alone. He's not here.
这里就我一个人 他不在
-He's… He'll be back in a few days. -You don't look very well, Victor.
-他…他几天后会回来 -维克多 你看着状态不大好
Oh, I've never felt better! I've never had a clearer mind! Come, come!
我的状态从来没这么好过！ 我的头脑清晰多了！快来！
Are you running a fever?
你发烧了吗？
I am just very excited to see you.
我只是看到你太激动了
I'm exalted. The spirits have lifted me so much.
我太高兴了 简直要飞起来了
Absolutely marvelous…
那东西太神奇了 我就知道能实现
Victor…
维克多
Victor. Victor.
维克多 请给我一点时间
Who hurt you?
是谁伤害了你？
I have to show you this, William.
威廉 你一定要看看这个
Let me organize it for you.
我先整理一下
And I have something to show to you.
我也有东西要给你看
I've spoken to the Royal Medical Society.
我跟英国皇家医学会的人聊过了
-They're interested in seeing you. -No, no, no, not yet.
-他们想见你 -现在还不行
I'm not quite ready yet.
我还没准备好
I thought that's what you always wanted.
我以为这是你一直以来的梦想
The man.
那个男人
-The man downstairs. -You saw him?
-楼下的那个男人 -你看到他了？
Is he a patient? A victim?
他是病人吗？是被你打伤的吗？
His wounds. You wounded him like that.
他身上好多伤口 你竟然下手那么重
No, no, no. It was the world that hurt him, Elizabeth.
不 伤害他的是这个世界 伊丽莎白
I… I gave him life.
我给了他生命
I gave him life.
Up, up, up.
起来
Come on.
来
There, there, there…
慢着
He's still getting used to his surroundings.
他还在适应周围的环境
It is strong, William.
它很强壮 威廉
-You did it. -It's so strong.
-你成功了 -非常强壮
You did it.
你成功了
All its systems are functional.
体内所有系统都正常运作
All healing.
伤口都在愈合
And the healing is erratic, yes.
愈合的状态不稳定
But exceptional.
但是非同寻常
Why is he chained here?
他为什么被拴在这里？
For his own safety and for mine,
为了保护他自己 还有我
and it's easy to clean and, uh, maintain it.
也更方便给它清洁维护
And it doesn't know any better.
很多事它还不懂
But you do.
但你懂
Does Harlander know?
哈兰德知道了吗？
We have to prepare everything for the moment he returns.
我们要在他回来之前把一切准备好…
-Of course. -And have everything presentable.
-当然 -…让一切都有模有样
Is it intelligent?
它有智慧吗？
Victor, is it intelligent?
维克多 它有智慧吗？
I can't fathom how exactly you did what you did,
我无法理解你是怎么做到的
but its dimension does not escape me.
但这无疑是一项壮举
Victor, did you ever ask yourself,
维克多 你有没有问过自己
of all the parts that make that man,
这个人的所有组成部分中
which one holds the soul?
哪块是灵魂藏身的地方？
No, I didn't.
我没问过
There's something so disquieting about that creature down there.
楼下那头怪物总让人感到不安
Askew, like a figure peeking around a funhouse mirror.
扭曲诡异 像个在哈哈镜里探头探脑的身影
But animated.
但很有活力
Animated by what?
是哪里来的活力？
Does it hurt?
痛吗？
A leaf?
叶子？
For me?
给我的吗？
Thank you.
谢谢
Isn't it beautiful?
是不是很美？
This is for me?
给我的吗？
I'm Elizabeth.
我是伊丽莎白
Can you say "Elizabeth"?
会说吗？伊丽莎白
Elizabeth.
伊丽莎白
My throat makes sounds.
从喉咙里发出声音
Elizabeth.
伊丽莎白
I'm going to go now.
我要走了
Eliza… beth.
伊丽莎…白
You should not go near it.
你不该靠近那东西的
"It"?
那东西？
It. Yes.
没错 那东西
I believe there is life in it, but not the spark of intelligence
那东西是活的 但没有智慧的火花
that I had intended.
我故意这么设计的
Perhaps not as you understand it.
可能不是你想象的那样
Something went wrong.
什么地方出了差错
A blockage, a suture, a connection.
阻塞了 缝合了 连通了
You, the great Victor Frankenstein, you made a mistake?
伟大的维克多·弗兰肯斯坦 还会犯错？
The Creature knows but one word, and one word alone.
那头怪物只会一个词 仅有的一个
"Victor, Victor, Victor, Victor."
维克多
It just parrots it without rhyme or reason.
只是莫名其妙地机械重复
Perhaps for the time being that word means everything to him.
也许在当下 那个词就是他的一切
What if in being anew, the spirit that animates him is simpler,
要是重生后的他 获得活力的源泉其实更简单
-purer-- -Purer?
-更纯粹… -纯粹？
Purer than that of the common man?
比普通人的更纯粹呢？
What if, unrestrained by sin,
要是他不受制于原罪
our creator's breath came into its wounded flesh directly?
而造物主为这具伤痕累累的血肉之躯 直接注入了生气呢？
Good God, Elizabeth.
天啊 伊丽莎白
If I could force myself to believe it,
要是我强迫自己信了你这话
it would be my inclination to see attraction in you for that thing.
我会觉得你是不是被这东西吸引了
Understanding.
好好理解一下
In those eyes I saw pain,
他的眼中有痛苦的情绪
and what is pain if not evidence of intelligence?
没有智慧 何来痛苦？
What about my pain?
那我的痛苦算什么？
What about what you have denied me?
被你拒绝算什么？
What my heart wants…
我的心想要什么？
Your heart?
你的心？
Of all the human anatomy,
所有人体结构中
that is the organ furthest from your understanding.
只有心最难捉摸
Only monsters play God, Baron.
男爵 只有怪物会扮演上帝
Purer than the common man, hmm?
比普通人更纯粹
And I, somehow, the villain. Mm-hmm.
不知怎的 我成了坏人
Your heart is pure?
你的心很纯粹？
I assure you it isn't.
我向你保证 并非如此
I should know. I put it there.
我知道 因为是我亲手放进去的
Up.
上去
Let us try again.
再试一下
Now give me your leg.
腿伸出来
Leg!
腿！
Give me your leg!
腿伸出来！
Pain is evidence of intelligence, is it not?
没有智慧 何来痛苦？
Well, let's test the theory.
行 测试一下这个说法吧
Give me your leg!
腿伸出来！
Leg!
腿！
Come on!
快点！
Give it to me, you beast!
伸出来 你个野兽！
Give me your leg!
腿伸出来！
Leg!
腿！
Victor!
维克多！
Victor! Victor!
What is it, Victor?
维克多 怎么了？
Come. Come.
来
I failed. I made a mistake.
我失败了 我犯了大错
-No, you didn't fail. I saw your papers. -I did.
-你没有失败 我看过你的图纸了 -失败了
-It's perfect. -The Creature is extremely dangerous.
-非常完美 -那头怪物极其危险
There's not… Victor.
没有…维克多
Let's wait for Harlander and discuss together.
我们等哈兰德回来 再一起讨论吧
William, there is something you should know.
威廉 有件事我得告诉你
Something I have to show you.
我得给你看一下
-Ha-- Harlander… -In a fit of rage, he killed him.
-哈兰德… -那头怪物突然暴怒 把他杀了
Do you understand now why I was hesitant to share this with you?
这下你知道 我为什么没有及时告诉你了吧？
And certainly not with Elizabeth.
当然也不敢让伊丽莎白知道
S… So what's to be done now?
那现在怎么办？
What?
什么？
-What's to be done? -"What's to be done"?
-现在怎么办？ -你说怎么办？
You must take Elizabeth back to Vienna.
你得带伊丽莎白回维也纳
Tell her something urgent came up and you have to leave immediately.
就说出了急事 必须马上走
Keep her in the dark.
千万别让她知道
For her own safety.
这是为了保护她
You have to do as I say.
必须照我说的办
We'll be back in no time. But for now, this is for the best.
我们很快就回来 但现在只能先走
Now get in the carriage, please.
请上马车吧
The Creature, what's its lifespan, you think?
你觉得那头怪物能活多久？
Brief. Very brief, I'm sure.
必然没多久
I have the most terrible feeling.
我有种很坏的预感
What is it?
怎么了？
Turn the carriage around.
让马车回头
You go to Vienna.
你一个人去维也纳吧
Turn the carriage around or I will jump. He's going to kill him.
让马车回头 否则我就跳车 他要杀了他
Say one word.
说个词吧
One word more. Anything.
再说一个 随便什么
Make me save you.
你说了 我就不杀你
-Victor.
维克多
Elizabeth.
伊丽莎白
Victor! Victor!
维克多！
Victor!
But that was not the end of it.
但故事并未结束
In seeking life, I created death.
我试着创造生命 结果造就了死亡
It would seem I need to address my men again.
看来又要和他们聊聊了
Don't worry.
别担心
They'll listen to me.
他们会听我的话的
No, no, stop! Do not harm him! I'm here.
住手！别伤害他！我在这里
Take me.
带走我吧
Go on, beast.
来吧 野兽
Kill us both. Confirm your maker's tale.
把我俩都杀了 证明造你的人说的都是真的
My maker… told his tale.
造我的人 说了他的故事
Then I will tell you mine.
那我也来说说我的
第二部分
那头怪物的故事
Victor!
维克多！
I called your name and understood I was alone.
我反复呼唤你的名字 终于发现这里只有我
-What is that? -Shoot at it!
-那是什么？ -开枪！
Shoot it!
开枪！
Did you get it?
打到了吗？
Where is it?
去哪了？
My wounds had healed.
身上的伤口愈合了
But I felt cold, so cold.
但我觉得寒冷刺骨
-Can you start the fire? -All right.
-能把火生起来吗？ -好
And I'll repair the corral as soon as I can.
我会尽快把畜栏修好
You all right, then? Did you get it?
你没事吧 打到了吗？
Nah, we looked everywhere. Couldn't find that thing.
没有 我们到处看了 就是找不到
Though we shot at it two times.
虽然我们朝它开了两枪
Blood trail died about a mile from here.
血迹在离这里一公里多的地方消失了
All right. Come in. Come in.
好 进来吧
We followed it for a while and then it disappeared. Gone.
我们跟了它一段时间 接着它就消失了
What was it? Was it a bear?
那是什么东西？熊吗？
That was no bear or human. I've never seen anything like it.
不是熊 也不是人类 我从没见过那样的东西
Was it a ghost, then?
那么是幽灵吗？
It was no ghost. We drew blood. It was flesh and bone.
不是 它流血了 说明它有血肉 有骨头
Come, come. Over here.
来这边
Tell me more about what you saw.
你还看到了什么
Anna-Maria, take your grandfather over by the fireplace.
安娜玛丽亚 带祖父去壁炉边
Make sure he's comfortable.
让他暖一暖
Over here, Grandfather.
到这边来 祖父
We went deep into the forest. Couldn't find it.
我们钻到了森林深处 还是没找到它
We will get it.
会抓到它的
-It'll take time. -Yeah.
-就是要花些时间 -好
Anna-Maria, come.
安娜玛丽亚 过来
Come, love. Help me outside.
宝贝 来带我出去
The old man moved me.
那位老人触动了我
And his unseeing eyes were full of wisdom.
他失明的双目充满智慧
These people possessed a sound.
这些人会发出一种声音
Used it to tell each other
用来和彼此
about feelings and ideas.
交流感受和想法
They called them words.
他们把这种声音叫言语
Pay attention.
注意看
What is this?
这是什么？
A boy.
一个男孩
-And again. -A boy.
-再说一遍 -一个男孩
Very good, my child.
很好 孩子
And this?
这个呢？
An… An eye.
一只…一只眼睛
-And again. -An eye.
-再说一遍 -一只眼睛
Yeah. Well done. Well done, my girl.
很好 乖孩子
-Eye. -And this one?
-眼睛 -这个呢？
The hand.
手
-Very good. -Hand.
-很好 -手
Give us a hand.
来搭把手
Tie a rope around the biggest one back there.
用绳子把最大的捆住带回去
I longed to be part of this family.
我渴望加入这个家庭
We'll need more kindling before the winter.
冬天之前要再多储备一些柴火
We'll take a few trips.
我们得跑几趟
To be their benefactor.
渴望帮他们的忙
We'll need larger trunks for the structure.
需要大一点的树干来搭这个
All right.
好
What could I possibly do for them?
我能为他们做点什么呢？
Anna-Maria! Father!
安娜玛丽亚！父亲！
Come! Come and see!
快来看啊！
Look, Anna-Maria!
看啊 安娜玛丽亚！
Look, there's more! Look!
看 还有呢！快看！
Who could have done this?
这会是谁送来的？
The Spirit of the Forest.
是森林精灵
We should thank him.
我们得谢谢他
Thank you.
谢谢你
Say, "Thank you, Spirit of the Forest."
说“谢谢你 森林精灵”
Thank you. Thank you, Spirit of the Forest.
谢谢你 森林精灵
Thank you.
谢谢
Come. Look over here.
来吧 看这里
Thank you.
谢谢你
From then on, I became their invisible guardian.
从此以后 我就成了 他们看不见的守护者
The Spirit of the Forest.
森林精灵
And on occasion, they too extended a small kindness towards me.
他们也不时对我释放小小的善意
Clothes, bread.
送上衣服、面包
And for a moment,
在那段时光
a brief, brief moment,
极为短暂的时光
the world and I were at peace.
我和这个世界相安无事
Come along. Come along.
跟上
In you go. Yeah.
进去吧 对
Make sure you close that gate.
记得关门
Who could have done this?
是谁做的呢？
The Spirit of the Forest, eh?
森林精灵吧
I got it.
我知道了
"And in the end, the proud young man
“最终 这个骄傲的年轻男子
could never find his missing hand."
再也找不到他丢失的那只手了
"It turned to stone, his fortune gone,
它变成了石头 他的财富消失了
and he lost his pride and lost his land."
他的骄傲 他的土地 都失去了”
Very good, my dear.
非常好 宝贝
Beautifully read. Now try this one.
读得真棒 再读下这个吧
Wolves.
狼来了
An idea,
某个想法
a feeling became clear to me.
某种感觉 在我心中愈发清晰
The hunter did not hate the wolf.
猎人并不憎恨狼
The wolf did not hate the sheep.
狼并不憎恨羊
But violence felt inevitable between them.
但相互之间的暴力冲突无可避免
Perhaps, I thought, this was the way of the world.
我想 也许这正是世界的法则
It would hunt you and kill you
你成为猎物 被杀
just for being who you are.
只是因为你的身份
The sheep will be sold by the end of the month, Father.
父亲 我月末就会把羊卖掉
Then I'll take you, Alma and Anna-Maria into town.
然后带着你 阿尔玛和安娜玛丽亚去镇上住
We'll go into the mountains,
我们要上山
hunt the wolves and be back at the end of winter.
去猎几头狼 冬末回来
I pray here alone every winter and this year will be no different.
我每年冬天都在这里祈祷 今年也一样
Please, Father, listen to reason.
父亲 求你了 听劝吧
You do what you must and so will I.
你们该怎么做就怎么做 我也一样
You stubborn old goat.
老顽固
It's just you and I now, Spirit.
现在只有你和我了 森林精灵
Just you and I.
就你和我了
And I had formed in my imagination many ways
我已经构想了无数种方式
I would present myself to the old man.
我要在这个老头面前现身
Would he fear me?
他会怕我？
Welcome me?
欢迎我？
Turn me away?
还是会赶我走呢？
Who goes there?
谁在那里？
With a single step, I entered a different world.
上前一步 我进入了完全不同的世界
One I had only seen from afar.
曾经我只能远远观望的世界
Please, who is it?
到底是谁？
Answer me.
出个声吧
Tell me.
告诉我
Why are you here?
你来干什么的？
Travel.
路过
Welcome, dear traveler.
亲爱的过客 欢迎你
Do not think me ungrateful for the company if I ask you to procure a chair.
请你自己找把椅子 不要觉得我怠慢了你
I… I find it difficult being a good host.
我没法周到待客
Yes.
没错
My… My sight has failed me.
我的眼睛看不见
But there is bread and brandy on the table.
桌上有面包和白兰地
Pray help yourself.
请自行享用
Bran… dy?
白兰地？
Your language.
听你说话
You have a hard time speaking it.
好像不大流利
Are you not from these parts?
你是不是从别的地方来的？
Are you afraid?
你害怕吗？
No need to be.
不用怕
What are you afraid of?
你在怕什么？
-Everything.
什么都怕
-Your…
你的…
Your hands are frozen
你的手好冷
and you've been hurt, have you not?
你还受伤了
Hurt?
受伤？
Yes. Your hands and face have scars
没错 你的手上和脸上都有伤疤
and you are wearing uniform.
你还穿着制服
Were you injured in battle?
是在战斗中受的伤吗？
You were hiding
你一直
in the mill gears, were you not?
躲在磨坊齿轮里面 对吧？
Yeah. Yeah. The Spirit of the Forest.
对 你就是森林精灵
Yes.
没错
I cannot judge of your countenance,
我看不到你的面容
but there is something in your voice
但听你的嗓音
which persuades me of your goodwill and kindness.
你肯定很善良
-Kindness? -Mm.
善良？
Stay with me.
留下来吧
Share my food and fire.
你可以吃我的东西 烤我的火
I would be delighted to share what little I have with you
我有的不多 但能跟你分享 我会很高兴的
and would be greatly helped by your companionship.
有你陪着我 对我也大有好处
And you… you could read to me.
你可以读书给我听
-Read? -Mm.
读书？
Make this your home and I your friend.
把这里当成自己家 把我当成朋友
Friend.
朋友
Friends.
And it was then that I read my first story,
就是在那时 我读到了我生命中第一个故事
and it was the first story.
也是《圣经》中的第一个故事
I read about a man named Adam and a woman named Eve,
故事的主人公是一个名叫亚当的男子 和名叫夏娃的女子
about their time in the first garden.
他们住在人类的第一个乐园里
I read about the rise of rival cities
我读到了两座城市崛起 相互竞争
and the collapse of a tower
一座高塔倒塌
and the wrath of a God.
上帝震怒毁城
And I read about men that fought dragons
我读到人类斗巨龙
and men who lost everything.
最终失去一切
And time passed
时光流逝
and fell away with the leaves of autumn.
如秋叶飘落
Have you never seen the snow, my dear friend?
亲爱的朋友 你见过下雪吗？
It makes the world clean… and new.
大雪荡涤一切 让世界焕然一新
"My name is Ozymandias, King of Kings."
“吾乃奥兹曼迪亚斯 万王之王
"Look on my works, ye Mighty, and despair."
盖世功业 敢叫天公折服
"No thing beside remains."
此外无一物
"Round the decay of that colossal wreck, boundless and bare."
但见废墟周围 寂寞平沙空莽莽
"The lone and level sands stretch far away."
伸向荒凉的四方
"My name is Ozymandias…"
吾乃奥兹曼迪亚斯”
Are there more books than this in the world?
世上哪里的书比这里还多？
A few more, I'm sure.
肯定还有一些地方
Not here.
不是这里
Last book on the left. Take it.
左边最后 就拿那本
We haven't got to it.
那本还没读过
Paradise Lost, Milton.
弥尔顿的《失乐园》
Man has questions for God.
人类对上帝有疑问
Even God has questions.
就连上帝自己也有疑问
I think he wanted answers and that is why he sent us his son.
我觉得上帝也想得到答案 所以才会派来自己的儿子
Death probably intrigued him.
或许他很想了解死亡
Suffering.
了解受苦受难
I want to know who I am.
我想知道我是谁
Where do I come from?
我从哪里来？
God took your memory just as I wish he would take mine away.
上帝拿走了你的记忆 而我多么希望我的记忆也被带走
Many years ago, I took a man's life.
多年前 我拿走了某个人的生命
A good man.
那是个好人
And I have been atoning for it since.
自那时起 我一直在赎罪
Forgive.
试着原谅
Forget.
试着忘记
The true measure of wisdom.
智慧真正的试金石
To know you have been harmed,
是知道自己受了伤害
by whom you have been harmed,
知道被谁伤害
and choose to let it all fade.
然后选择让一切烟消云散
But I cannot forget what I cannot remember.
但记不起来的东西 要怎么忘记
Do you recall nothing?
你什么都记不起来吗？
In my dreams…
在睡梦中
…I… see memories.
我…能窥见记忆
Different men.
各种各样的人
All… pieces.
都是…一些片断
I…
我…
I remember f… fire and water.
我记得有火 有水
And sand under my feet.
脚下有沙子
And a word.
还有一个词
A single word.
就一个词
What is it?
什么词？
Victor.
维克多
Go to it.
去找到它
The word.
维克多
And then I learned it.
然后我终于体会到了
The horror of the truth.
真相的可怖
I understood that I was nothing.
我明白了 自己一无是处
A wretch.
是个可怜虫
A blot.
是块不起眼的污渍
Not even of the same nature as man.
甚至算不上是人类
This hurt clung to my mind.
这种痛苦缠绕着我
It never let go.
永不消散
Then I saw it.
然后我看见了
Your name.
你的名字
"Victor Frankenstein."
“维克多·弗兰肯斯坦”
And where to find you.
知道了到哪里能找到你
No!
不！
You came back.
你回来了
I found what I am.
我知道我是谁了
What I am made from.
知道我是什么造就的了
I am… the child of a charnel house.
我…我是尸骨堆里造出来的
A wreckage.
我是残骸
Assembled from refuse and the discarded dead.
是用垃圾和被丢弃的尸体拼凑出来的
A monster.
是怪物
I know what you are.
我知道你是谁
A good man.
你是个好人
And… you are my friend.
也是我的朋友
Friend?
朋友？
Friend.
朋友
What is that thing?
那是什么？
The-- The thing from the woods?
是森林里的那东西吗？
What have you done to him?
你把他怎么了？
Don't move.
别动
Quick! Reload! Kill it!
快！上膛！杀了它！
There was silence again,
一切重回寂静
and then… merciless life.
而冷酷无情的生活还将继续
How long did I die for?
我死了多久？
I do not know.
不知道
But I saw my injuries healed.
但我看到身上的伤口愈合了
The cold winter air stung in my lungs.
冬日的寒风直灌入肺
I felt lonelier than ever,
孤独感更甚以往 且前所未有
because for every man there was but one remedy to all pain:
因为对世人而言 治愈一切痛苦的良药
Death, a gift you too had denied me.
唯有死亡 而这恩赐你也狠心剥夺
Envy rose within me
我的内心涌起羡慕之情
and decided to demand a single grace from you.
遂决意向你索求一份恩典
My creator.
我的缔造者
I would demand… a companion.
我想要…一个同伴
I need you to get up.
起来吧
Yes, of course. Of course.
好的
The wedding will start soon and I want you by my side.
婚礼马上要开始了 你得陪在我身边
It's hard to believe,
要不是你天性善良
if not for your kind nature.
我都不敢相信这话是你说的
I've spoken to a few guests about the inquest.
我跟几位宾客说了调查的事
About the explosion.
关于那场爆炸的调查
The majority accept it for what it was.
他们中的大多数都接受了官方的说法
And what was it, William?
官方怎么说 威廉？
The past, Victor.
都过去了 维克多
A terrible accident.
那是场可怕的意外
I intend to sell the estate.
我想卖了那座庄园
All we have is each other.
我们只有彼此了
I want you to throw the petals everywhere.
往四面八方撒
Throw them everywhere.
到处都撒一点
Go upstairs and do some more of that.
到楼上去 再多撒点
I know it is bad luck to see the bride before the ceremony.
我知道 婚礼前见新娘会带来厄运
Only for the groom.
只对新郎起效
Yes, that's right. Not for me.
没错 对我没用
Hello, Elizabeth.
你好啊 伊丽莎白
I've rarely felt remorse before and now I feel little else. I…
之前我从未感受过懊悔 而现在懊悔充斥了我的内心
A fever gripped me for so long, but it has passed,
我的心被一种冲动占据已久 但这种感觉已经消散
and I see you now as I should.
我可以正常地面对你了
For whatever it's worth, I… I wish you and my little brother,
无论如何 我衷心祝愿
who I love more than life, the very best.
你和我挚爱的弟弟幸福
You may like to believe you do.
你大可以自欺欺人
And I dread to even hear it.
而我都害怕听见
On my wedding day, I ask you but for a single grace.
今天是我的大喜之日 我就求你一件事
No more lies.
别撒谎了
-I-- I want to tell you-- -Leave my chambers now.
-我想告诉你… -给我出去
-Elizabeth. -Leave!
-伊丽莎白 -出去！
Come out of the shadows,
出来 别躲在暗处
if you are here.
如果你在这里
Are you here to thank me?
你是来感谢我的吗？
You survived and are intelligent enough to have found me.
你活下来了 还变得足够聪明 都找到我了
I made you well.
是我造得好
I need you to make a companion for me.
我要你给我造一个同伴
One like me.
像我这样的
A com… A companion?
同伴？
I see.
我知道了
Another monster.
再来个怪物
Yes.
对
We can be monsters together.
让我们两个怪物作伴
I have found sanity at such a cost,
我付出巨大代价 才找回了理智
and you here… are madness calling me back.
你却想让我再回疯狂
I cannot die.
我死不了
And I cannot live…
只有我自己
alone.
我也活不好
In you I have created something truly horrible.
我造出了非常恐怖的东西
Not something.
不是东西
Someone.
是人
You made someone.
你造出了人
Me.
就是我
Whatever puzzle I am, creator, I think.
不管我多么让人费解 但我会思考
I feel.
有感受
I have this sole petition…
我只有这一个请求
Make one like me.
再造一个像我一样的
And then what?
然后呢？
Procreation.
生育
Reproduction.
繁殖
A home?
建立家庭？
A grave?
建造坟墓？
Death begetting death begetting death.
死亡与破坏不断上演
A race of devils propagated upon the earth.
恶魔的种族在地球上蔓延
Obscenity perpetuating itself.
肮脏永不断绝
I am obscene to you, but to myself I simply am.
在你看来我很肮脏 在我看来我只是我
Begone!
滚开！
Never again will I make something like you, wicked and deformed.
我绝不会再造一个 像你这么邪恶丑陋的东西
Then it is still all about your will, Victor.
这一切还不都是 源自你的执念 维克多
That horrible, horrible will that birthed me condemns me now?
凭恐怖的执念造就我 如今又固执地谴责我
The miracle is not that I should speak, but that you would ever listen!
我开口说话算不上奇迹 你愿意倾听才算！
If you are not to award me love, then I will indulge in rage.
你不愿赐我伴侣 我将倾泻怒火
And mine is infinite.
无穷无尽的怒火
Step aside.
请让一让
Victor.
维克多
What's going on?
怎么了？
You…
你
It's you.
是你
Elizabeth, move away from it!
伊丽莎白 离它远一点！
No!
不要！
It attacked her! It attacked her!
那东西袭击了她！
Take me with you.
带我走吧
Oh, my God!
天啊
No, let me… I can save you.
别动 让我来…我能救你
I can save you.
我会救活你
From what?
救我？
From you?
是害我吧
I fear you, Victor.
我怕你 维克多
No, no…
不
I always have.
一直怕你
Every ounce of madness and destruction.
你的每一次疯狂和破坏
The very conflagration that devoured everything.
如同大火 足以吞噬一切
It all came from you.
一切都是你造成的
You are the monster.
你才是怪物
My place was never in this world.
我和这个世界格格不入
I sought and longed for something I could not quite name.
我一直渴望并追寻着 一种说不清道不明的东西
But in you, I found it.
可在你身上 我找到了这种东西
To be lost and to be found,
丢失并被寻回
that is the lifespan of love.
这就是爱的宿命
And in its brevity,
其短暂
its tragedy…
其悲剧性
this has been made eternal.
造就永恒
Better this way… to fade…
就让我在你的注视之中
with your eyes gazing upon me.
死去吧
She is gone and I long to follow.
她走了 我也想随她而去
You gave me life unwanted.
你给了我备受唾弃的生命
I give that back to you.
我这就还给你
You thought me a monster.
你当我是怪物
Now I return the favor.
就让我这个怪物来回敬你
Kill me! Kill me now, do it!
杀了我 现在就杀了我
I will make you bleed.
我要让你流血
I will make you humble.
让你卑微求饶
You may be my creator,
你是造了我
but from this day forward, I will be your master.
但从今天起 你要听我的话
You hunted me past the forests,
你为了猎杀我
past the mountains,
翻山越岭
past frozen horizons,
横跨冰川
until there was nothing left.
直到天地间
Just you… and me.
只剩你我
I need ammunition.
给我来点子弹
Sharpen this.
这个磨快一点
Three cans of condensed milk, some firewood.
来三罐炼乳 一点木柴
And six sticks of dynamite.
还有六筒炸药
Six?
六筒？
What are you hunting?
你要打什么？
Big game.
大的
No! No! No!
不！
Victor.
维克多
You only listen when I hurt you.
只有被我伤到 你才会听我说话
This. You put your faith in this.
这个 你相信这东西
You think this will unmake me.
能够摧毁我
Light it then and hope it does, but if it does not,
点着吧 希望如你所愿 但如果失败了
I will come for you again.
我会再来找你
Light it!
点起来！
Now… run.
快跑吧
So, there you were, broken and discarded.
好了 如今你残破不堪
And I,
而我
alive again.
又活过来了
I could feel my singed flesh regrowing.
我能感到 被灼伤的血肉在重新生长
The crackling of my bones resetting.
断裂的骨头重回原位
The murmur of my blood pumping through my incessant heart.
永不停息的心脏泵出汩汩的血流
And once more finding no mercy,
再次发现无人怜悯
I had but one path.
我只剩一条路可走
And here we are.
我们终究走到了这一步
Spent and done.
精疲力尽 一无所有
No more in us to give or take.
再没有什么可以付出或索取了
The blood outside the tent…
帐篷外的血迹
It is mine.
是我的
All mine.
都是我的
I will bleed.
我将流血
Ache.
疼痛
Suffer.
受苦
You see, it will never end.
永无尽头
I am sorry.
对不起
Regret consumes me.
我的内心充满懊悔
And I now regard my life for what it was.
如今我终于能正视我的生命了
You will go now, creator.
缔造者 你要走了
Fade away.
要消失了
It will all be but a brief moment.
一切都只是短暂的一瞬
My birth. My grief.
我的诞生 我的悲伤
Your loss.
你的损失
I will not be punished.
我不会受惩罚
Nor absolved.
也无法摆脱罪责
What hope I had,
我的希望
what rage…
我的怒火
It is all nothing.
都毫无意义
The tide that brought me here now comes to take you away.
那股造就我的浪潮 如今要带你走了
Leaving me stranded.
留下搁浅的我
Forgive me.
原谅我吧
My son.
吾儿
And if you have it in your heart, forgive yourself into existence.
如你有意 也请宽恕自己的存在
If death is not to be, then consider this, my son.
吾儿 如果无法死去 还请细思此事
While you are alive,
既然活着
what recourse do you have but to live?
除了活下去 还有别的选择吗？
Live.
活着
Say my name.
说出我的名字吧
My father gave me that name,
我的名字是父亲起的
and it meant nothing.
但其实并无意义
Now I ask you to give it back to me…
现在 我请求你把这个名字还给我
one last time.
最后一次了
The way you said it at the beginning.
就像最开始 你把这个名字
When it meant the world to you.
当成全世界时那样呼唤我
Victor.
维克多
I forgive you.
我宽恕你
Rest now, Father.
安息吧 父亲
Perhaps now,
或许现在
we can both be human.
我们都能算作是人了
Weapons down.
放下武器
-Put the weapons down! -I am responsible for my men.
-放下武器 -我要为我的人负责
He can leave.
让他走
We are free!
船能动了！
我们自由了！
Captain…
船长
What are your orders?
您的指令是？
Man the sails.
扬帆起航
Turn around.
掉头
Do you want to tell the men?
您要亲自宣布吗？
Men!
大家听好！
We're sailing home!
我们开船回家
我们回家了
“心会破碎 但破碎后依然跳动”
-拜伦勋爵
影片编剧兼导演
吉列尔莫·德尔托罗
基于玛丽·雪莱所著
小说《科学怪人》改编
制片人
吉列尔莫·德尔托罗
J·迈尔斯·戴尔
斯科特·斯图伯
摄影
达恩·劳斯特森
剪辑
伊万·希夫
配乐
亚历山大·德斯普拉
出品公司
网飞公司
制作公司
双重挑战公司
德米洛影业 & 蓝草七号影业
吉列尔莫·德尔托罗
导演作品
《科学怪人》
主演
奥斯卡·伊萨克 饰 维克多
雅各布·艾洛蒂 饰 怪物
主演
米娅·高斯 饰 伊丽莎白
费利克斯·卡默雷尔 饰 维克多弟弟威廉
主演
大卫·布拉德利 饰 盲人
拉尔斯·米科尔森 饰 船长安德森
主演
克利斯汀·康佛瑞 饰 幼年维克多
查尔斯·丹斯 饰 维克多父亲
主演
克里斯托弗·瓦尔兹 饰 赞助人哈兰德
官方字幕翻译：涅伽达
蒙太奇字幕组 & 远鉴字幕组 联合出品
双语合并 & 后期：novaeye  内容补充：小p
本片官方字幕尚有提升空间  原创译制正在进行中
可加入我们的Telegram群组一起制作：MontageSubs
（网飞公司）